Guide to the Joseph C. Wetherby papers, 1930 - 1976 UA.29.02.0030
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph C. Wetherby papers
1930 - 1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wetherby, Joseph C., 1910-1976
UA.29.02.0030
4.6 Linear Feet
Joseph Cable Wetherby served as Associate Professor of English at Duke University from 1947-1976. The papers consist of correspondence, printed matter, speeches, clippings, minutes, memoranda, teaching aids and other teaching materials, student papers, photographs, research notes, and writings. Major subjects include the teaching of English to international students at Duke, broadcasting and the development of the WDBS radio station at Duke University, and the Duke University Debate Team, which Wetherby coached for over 20 years. English.
5500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Joseph C. Wetherby papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1977.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1910 Born 2 May, Bellingham, Washington
1930-1936 Student, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan; B.A., Speech, 1934; M.A., Speech, 1936
1936 Married Carol Van Sickle
1936-1942 Assistant Professor of Speech, Oklahoma State University
1942-1946 Active Duty, U.S. Navy, as Lieutenant
1946-1947 Director of Radio, Wayne State University
1947-1976 Associate Professor of English, Duke University
1948 Published "In the Realm of Radio", in Southern Speech Journal
1952-1976 Regional Governor, Delta Sigma Rho Tau Kappa Alpha (forensic honorary), reelected 1976
1953 Graduate study in Speech and Psychology, University of Florida
1957 Summer, Guest Professor of Speech, Wake Forest University
1960 President, Southern Speech Association
1960-1967 Temporary Action Duty, U.S. Navy, as Lieutenant Commander; Head of English Dept., U.S. Naval Preparatory School, Naval Enlisted Scientific Education Program
1961 Published "Academic Status Seekers", in Southern Speech Journal
1963 Published "Debate 1984", in The Speaker
1967 Director Producer for Durham Savoyards Ltd. (Gilbert and Sullivan Shows): Iolanthe (1967); Gondoliers (1974)
1976 April: Debate Team wins National Championship
1976 Distinguished Service Award of Delta Sigma Rho Tau Kappa Alpha
1976 Died 12 October, Duke University
Wetherby was active in many professional organizations during his career, including the Speech Association of America, Educational Theatre Association (Honorary Life Member), Southern Speech Association, Delta Sigma Rho Tau Kappa Alpha, Sigma Alpha Eta (Speech and Hearing Honorary), American Forensic Association, North Carolina Speech Association (President), and Association of Teachers of English to Speakers of Other Languages.
Collection Overview
The Wetherby Papers contain printed material (including pamphlets, brochures, flyers, programs, speeches, and clippings), correspondence, minutes, memoranda, teaching aids and other teaching materials, student papers, photographs, research notes, writings, and other papers. Inclusive dates for the collection are ca. 1930 to 1976, with the bulk of material from 1947 to 1976.
These papers chiefly reflect Wetherby's interest in three major areas: teaching English as a foreign language, broadcasting, and debating. In the first category falls material on grammar and enunciation (including numerous exercises, tests, and other teaching aids), speech and hearing pathology, and a small number of administrative papers dealing with the teaching of English to international students at Duke University. In the area of broadcasting, there are clippings, course descriptions, lecture material, and printed material on the history of radio and television; its methods, principles, and policies; legal status; government policies affecting broadcasting; and audience and market research. Wetherby also kept clippings, printed matter, and copies of speeches on communications and broadcasting in general, as well as on specialized topics such as TV violence and cigarette advertising.
Files concerning the history of Duke University include materials on a proposed FM station for the campus (1957-1968), as well as selected student papers on such topics as broadcasting at Duke, the Vigil of 1968, and the Associated Students of Duke University in a conflict with WDBS. There are also a number of selected student papers on various aspects of communications, broadcasting, and the persuasive speaking.
There is a card file on members of the Debate Team with their records by opponent and tournament, and a small amount of material (correspondence, records, circulars, a telegram) on the West Point National Tournament for 1962 to 1964.
Useful information regarding a significant incident early in Wetherby's tenure as debate coach will be found in William King, Not fit to debate? National debate topic on Communist China gets hackles up, in the Duke Alumni Register, vol. 65, no. 2, Nov.- Dec. 1978. The article deals with Wetherby's defense of the right of collegiate debaters to argue this sensitive topic in 1954, at the height of the McCarthy era. Wetherby appeared on the See It Now program of Edward R. Murrow on CBS Television.
Wetherby coached three teams from Duke University which appeared on national television on the College Bowl series, in 1955, 1960, and 1968. Some materials in the collection deal with the logistics of these teams' travel and appearances, and on the operation of the telecasts.
Gathered in separate folders as well as scattered throughout the collection is a large amount of printed material in the form of brochures, handbooks, pamphlets, newsletters, and copies of speeches. Included is material from organizations like the National Association of Broadcasters, the Federal Communications Commission, the Southern Speech Association (later the Southern Speech Communication Association), and the Speech Communication Association. The collection from the Southern Speech Association and its successor organization includes a consecutive run of programs for annual conventions from 1951 to 1976. The material on the Speech Communication Association includes consecutive issues from 1968 to 1976 of Free Speech, a newsletter of this organization's Commission on Freedom of Speech.
During the 1960s, Wetherby frequently was sent to regional high schools to promote Duke University to prospective students.
Related Material
Debate Team records.
University Archives, Duke University.
WDBS records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Debates and debating -- Study and teaching; College radio stations -- United States; Radio broadcasting; English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers; Broadcasting -- Study and teaching; Photographs; Speeches; Students, Foreign; Clippings (information artifacts); WDBS (Radio station: Durham, N.C.); Duke University. Debate Team; Duke University. Department of English; Wetherby, Joseph C., 1910-1976; Wetherby, Joseph C., 1910-1976
- Teaching Activities, ca. 1930-1976
  Scope and Contents note
  Memoranda, correspondence, cards, reports, lists, newsletters, brochures, pamphlets, tests, exercises, minutes, clippings, speeches, plays, manuals, student papers, magazines, and other papers. The bulk of the materials dates from Wetherby's years at Duke University, 1947-1976. See also related materials in the 1977 Addition.
  - English as a Foreign Language (English 100). (Box 1)
    - Administrative, 1954-1970 (Box 1)
    - Blank certification forms (Box 1)
    - Testing, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
    - Exercises (Box 1)
    - Essays by foreign students (Box 1)
    - Language lab. English medical tapes. Contents (Box 1)
    - Ball Committee (Committee on Teaching of English as a Foreign Language), 1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence on request to send English medical books to Hungary, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - English instruction. Statistical profile and other papers. (Box 1)
      Includes minutes of one meeting in 1964 of International Students Advisory Committee, ca. 1964
    - Speech for Foreign and Bilingual Studies of the Speech Association of America, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
    - TESOL (Teachers of English to Speakers of Other Languages), 1964-1970 (Box 1)
    - TOEFL (Testing of English as a Foreign Language), 1960-1968 (Box 1)
    - NAFSA (National Association for Foreign Student Affairs), Visitation, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Teaching exercises and tests.
    - Articulation (Box 1)
    - Announcers' tests (Box 2)
      Includes further material on articulation and some material on speech pathology
    - Grammar and composition (Box 2)
      Includes exercises, tests, manual
  - Broadcasting.
    - English 160-170 (Broadcasting). Blank questionnaires (Box 2)
    - Broadcasting Notes binder, 1950-1969 (Box 2)
    - "Broadcasting History" tape table of contents [tape not in this collection] (Box 2)
    - University of Akron Television Instructor's Reference Handbook, 1962 (Box 2)
    - TV Violence, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Cigarette advertising, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Federal Communications Commission, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Broadcast seminar, 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Measurement" (binder). Audience research, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
    - National Association of Broadcasters, 1964-1970 (Box 3)
    - Association for Professional Broadcasting Education, 1964-1970 (Box 3)
    - Broadcasting: Notes, speeches etc., 1952-1972 [2 folders] (Box 3)
    - American Research Bureau, Channel One, 1964-1968 (Box 3)
  - Drama, poetry, oratory, persuasive speech, and public speaking.
    - Drama: script form, stage plays for TV, plays, censorship of plays, 1910-1959 (Box 3)
    - Poetry recital (story) (Box 3)
    - English 118. Persuasive speech, Exam, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Barnwell, Robert. Oratory (Box 3)
    - Aristotle on Youth (Box 3)
    - Clichs (Box 3)
    - Notes on parliamentary procedure (Box 3)
    - Discussion (Box 4)
  - Speech and hearing pathology.
    - Tests, exercises, papers (Box 4)
    - Stuttering (Box 4)
    - Proposed educational psychology program, 1966-1968 (Box 4)
    - Manuals: hearing test, audiometer. (Box 4)
    - Bibliographical file (See also card file boxes) (Box 4)
  - Student papers.
    - Topics concerning Duke University
      - Arena, R. Broadcasting at Duke University. 1969. (Box 4)
      - Armstrong, W.L. Head Cheerleader Campaign: On the Road to '76. ca. 1975. (Box 4)
      - Fader, B. The Duke Football Network. No date. (Box 4)
      - Hall, S.T. Media and the Duke Student. 1968. (Box 4)
      - Klein, R.P. Analysis of Persuasive Speaking Techniques in a College Demonstration. 1970. (Box 4)
      - Regan, P. The Life and Times of a College Radio Station: Some Views and Thoughts on the Recent Controversy between WDBS and ASDU. No date. (Box 4)
      - Robbins, J. The Duke Vigil and the Creation of a Psychological Mob. ca. 1968. (Box 4)
      - Schwartz, A.D. The Duke Sports Network. 1971. (Box 4)
    - Student papers on broadcasting and persuasive speaking (Box 4-5)
    - Language Lab Committee, 1964-1969 (Box 6)
    - Speech, general (Box 6)
  - Educational organizations.
    - Institute of International Education. Overseas Magazine, 1963 (Box 6)
    - National Education Association, Project English, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Other Teaching.
    - Navy, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
    - American Institute of Banking. Durham chapter, 1967-1973 (Box 6)
- Non-Teaching Activities, 1951-1976
  Pamphlets, brochures, correspondence, clippings, programs, newsletters, lists, bills, photos, application forms, clippings, and other papers. See also related materials in the 1977 Addition.
  - Speech associations.
    - North Carolina Speech Association, 1950-1957 (Box 6)
    - Southern Speech Association (SSA, later Southern Speech Communication Association) Radio Television Film Interest Group, ca. 1960-1969 (Box 6)
    - SSA Programs and other printed material, 1951-1976 (Box 6)
    - Speech Association of America, Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 6)
    - Speech Association of America, Committee of Fifty, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
    - Printed material, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
    - Speech Communication Association, 1968-1976 (Box 6)
      Includes the Free Speech newsletter for same years.
  - Debate Team.
    - West Point National Tournament, 1962-1964 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, ca. 1958-1976 (Box 7)
    - College Bowl teams, Correspondence and other papers, 1955-1969 (Box 7)
    - College Bowl teams, Sample questions, instructions, 1955-1967 (Box 7)
  - Radio at Duke.
    - Proposed FM station, 1957-1968 (Box 7)
    - Radio honorary fraternity, Alpha Epsilon Rho, 1963-1973 (Box 7)
    - Student Contacts Committee, 1960-1967 (Box 7)
    - Long Wetherby Research Grant Request, 1968 (Box 7)
- 1977 Addition, circa 1930-1976
  - J.C. Wetherby. Writings, Notes. Elocution, Rhetoric, "Executive's Guide," ca. 1930-1970 (Box 7)
    Some of these writings may date from Wetherby's time as a student.
  - Photos, clippings, ca. 1950-1975 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1963, undated (Box 7)
  - Obituary clippings, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Debate Team Records, 1948, 1953-1976 (Box 8)
  - Course material (Box 9)
    Some course materials mixed; each folder should be examined for specific course material
    - English
      - 100, 1959-1975 (Box 9)
      - 139, 1941-1975 (Box 9)
      - 140S, 1959-1967 (Box 9)
      - 150, 1943-1976 (Box 9)
        Contains press clippings on Terry Sanford campaign for the U.S. Presidency, 1976
      - 151, 1957 (Box 9)
      - 160, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Broadcasting
      - 171-172, 1953-1974 (Box 9)
      - 171, 1949-1969 (Box 9)
      - 172 Letters, 1959-1970 (Box 9)
        Contains letter from Jesse R. Helms
      - 172 Quiz, 1956-1976 (Box 9)
  - American Forensic Association, 1951-1976 (Box 10)
  - Broadcast Education Association, 1963-1976 (Box 10)
  - Broadcast Music Inc., 1968-1970 (Box 10)
  - Broadcast Pioneers, 1971-1976 (Box 10)
  - Broadcasting Magazine, 1963-1976 (Box 10)
  - International Studies Institute, 1964-1975 (Box 10)
  - Campus Studies Institute, 1974-1976 (Box 10)
  - CATV, 1969-1973 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1948-1968 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1968-1976 (Box 10)
  - Cultural Arts Committee, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Debate, 1976 (Box 10)
  - Foreign Broadcasting, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
  - Friday Luncheon Group, 1970-1976 (Box 10)
  - Guidelines Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 10)
  - Louisburg, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Ted Minah Committee, 1972-1976 (Box 10)
  - NCFA, 1976-1977 (Box 10)
  - Positions Open, Assistantship Applications, 1973-1975 (Box 10)
  - Psychological Tests (Box 10)
  - Remedial Reading (Box 10)
  - Rev. Paul Seitz--Jolo (Smith), 1972-1976 (Box 10)
  - Southern Speech Association, 1948-1963 (Box 10)
  - Southern Speech Communication Association
    - Ex Presidents' Club, 1969-1976 (Box 10)
    - Luncheon, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
    - Radio-TV-Film, 1960, 1970 1973 (Box 10)
  - WDBS
    - 1971-1975 (Box 10)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 10)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 10)
    - Management Board (Box 10)
  - WDBS Binders, 1971-1974 (Box 10)
    Include budget, correspondence, clippings, FCC application, minutes of Management Board
  - Outlines for Speech in Schools, 1936 (Box 10)
  - Notebooks (Box 10)
    3 binders and 1 notebook contain notes on speech, persuasive speaking, semantics, speech pathology; tests; syllabi; outlines of books; lessons; and other papers. These are either lecture notes or class notes made by Wetherby as a student.
  - Unfoldered material (Box 10)
    Loose sheets now grouped in a folder: lesson plans, bibliographies, diagrams, tests, notes on various phases of speech and speech pathology. Some of these materials may stem from Wetherby's time as a student.